hey what's up guys my name is Archana
welcome back to another C++ video it's
been ages since the last one gonna get
back into it now though dynamic casting
that's what we're gonna be talking about
today you guys don't know what casting
is in general in C++ I've got a video
about that so definitely check that out
and familiarize yourself with that
before you move on to this video if
you're not familiar with the type system
in general I have a few videos about
that as well because casting is to do
with types casting is a way for us to
convert between the types that we use in
C++ so you need to make sure that you
kind of understand how the type system
works and more so maybe the point that
the type system isn't something that is
particularly enforced in C++ it's
something that sales class kind of gives
us as a way to protect our code but it's
not something that we have to
necessarily stick to or use because we
can freely cast between types of any
types like if we so choose but dynamic
casting is provided to us as some
somewhat of like a safety net really for
when we want to do a specific type of
casting now I've gone through kind of
C++ style casts there's two kind of ways
to cast there's a c-style cast which is
just when you write your new type in
brackets before a variable but then
there's also the simplest I'll cast like
static cast Const casts I'll make
probably more videos about that but
dynamic cast is a C++ style cast that
only works in C++ doesn't work in C and
it doesn't extra work to make sure that
well like the way that we actually cast
right it's some it's a it's actually a
valid cast we don't just cast between
two types and and whatever happens
happens it's not like that it actually
does some validation for us to ensure
that cast is valid now whether or not
you use dynamic cast is again totally up
to you I want to give you some points to
kind of I guess educate you to a sense
of whether or not you should be using
that if that's something you want to do
but more so a dynamic cast is is quite a
it's it's a tool that's more like a
function it's important to realize that
it's not just like a cast that is done
at like compile time it's evaluated at
runtime and because of that it does have
an Associated runtime cost I might even
make a video in the
future comparing the performance of this
normal kind of static cast versus that
dynamic cast because of course since the
dynamic cast does extra work it does
kind of come with a small performance
cost and that's normal but what dynamic
cast does is specifically it's used for
casts along the inheritance hierarchy
now if you don't know what inheritance
is in civil puzzle what classes are in
C++ check out my video on inheritance
and on classes and all that stuff
because that will help you out but
essentially what that means is if I have
a class that is a subclass of another
class and I want to either cast to the
base type or from the base type to a
derived type that's where I can actually
use a dynamic cast right so let's just
say we have an entity we have an empty
class which is like the class for kind
of all of our entities in our game and
then we have like a player class and
maybe like an enemy class and they're
both entities so they derive from the
entity class right if I just want to
cast a player object back to an entity
object that that's easy I mean a player
already has the type entity so that that
can be done implicitly no casting is
necessary although if we wanted to we
could still use dynamic casts to do it
now
the other way around is where things get
a little bit more complicated so by the
other way around I mean if we have an
entity instance and we want to cast it
to a player we have no way of knowing
whether or it's a player right it's as
far as we know it is an entity pointer
right it's an entity instance is an
instance of an entity object right so
what is an entity object well it could
be of type entity could just be an
entity could be neither player right or
enemy right could just be an MC but it
also could be a player or it could be an
enemy that's totally valid we might have
made it a player we might have made it
an enemy or it could be a thief it could
be one of three types if we want to say
that actually I'm gonna cost this two
player we don't know if it is a player
or not the compiler has to either
believe us and if we're wrong let's just
say it was an enemy and we try and
access data that is unique to player or
a function that modifies doubt of this
unique two player our program will
probably crash and it'll be like a
disaster so because of that dynamic cost
is actually used
to validate that so what happens is if
we have an entity instance that is
actually an enemy right but we cast it
we try and cast it to a player using
dynamic cast that cast will fail and
that dynamic cast will return a null
pointer will just return zero and then
we can validate that or do whatever we
want so basically we could use it to
check to see if an object is a given
type so in other words I can try and do
a dynamic cast on that entity object to
convert it to player and then check to
see if that returns not with it returns
null that it's not a player right this
is a lot of stuff is more easily
explained encouraged so let's just dive
in take a look at a basic kind of setup
in which this might be useful and how we
could actually use dynamic casting okay
so what does a blank C++ project here
because I really wanted to kind of show
you guys everything so if we do what I
just described if we have like an entity
right if we have a player which is an MC
so a public entity and then we'll also
have that enemy class that I talked
about which is also going to be an su
right now
in terms of the data that these will
have if it's not even required for us to
actually add any data so I probably
wanted just to keep this brief I think
because it's not really worth going into
that stuff but basically the idea is we
have three different types that they're
probably filled with functions filled
with data that is unique to their
specific types how do I make an entity
well let's just say I want to make a
player I can just type in player player
equals new player now for this video
we're just gonna be using raw pointers I
might make a video in the future about
dynamic casting with smart pointers but
this video just can't cover kind of the
original dynamic cast that is used with
the raw pointers so we have a player
right now the thing is this player
already has two types it has both entity
and player associated with it it's
actually even got like a type list thing
as well which we might talk about later
but it's got the those two types and T
and player so what I could do is easily
just change this to entity right oh I
can make an entity II a people player
right implicit cost however once I've
done that if I want to go back to player
I can't easily do that so I can type in
player P equals E right that's gonna
give me an error
why because well I have to
the different types the reason is that
this could have easily been an enemy you
know what if I do
MC easy one or whatever equals new enemy
all right what happens here what about
what happens if I do a one right
we don't it's still an entity but is it
a player is it an enemy we don't really
know at this at this point so because of
that system we have to actually reassure
the compiler by saying that hey it is a
player now in this case there this is
dangerous
because E one's actually an enemy and so
if we cast it to a player this will
initially work and in fact if enemy has
a function that like player also has or
MC also has and we try and run that
function it'll probably work we probably
won't even notice any issues with it but
if we try and do something that is
unique to player that enemy doesn't have
such as access certain data members that
only player has a not enemy since the
underlying type is actually enemy our
program will likely crash or do some
really weird things that we really don't
want it to do so because of that we can
again instead of using R or casts or
even like a static class because you can
still use you know a static cast with
this like that I mean that's fine
instead about what we can do is swap
this out for a dynamic cast right now if
we try to do that at this rate it's
gonna tell us that it needs to have a
polymer off the class site because
dynamic cast only works with polymer for
class types how do we do that well we
basically need to have some kind of
virtual function table that actually
tell us that it is in fact a polymorphic
class type so we can make this we need
to say virtual void you know print name
or something like this doesn't really
matter but the point is that we'll make
this class have a V table and thus
there's stuff to override which means
that is it's a polymorphic type and we
can use dynamic casting with it again if
this was a real entity class it would
definitely have virtual functions so
this is just making it a little bit more
realistic as well so we can cast it
right so we've got our e which is a
player or we can use a one which is that
and actually actually an enemy so we
could say actually player just to make
this a little bit more clear and then we
could see it say actually enemy all
right so if we try and get our our enemy
into a player this
would fail right but if we try and
convert this player to a player that
should work even though they're both at
them at the moment they're both entities
okay so let's take a look at what this
code will do if we were to execute it
I'll put a breakpoint here and hit f5
and of course you should make sure that
my name is variables different things
okay so this caste should fail right
because this is actually an enemy and
we're trying to cast it to a player so
f10 and you can see this returns null
the cast didn't work however if I try
and do it here you can see that p1 is in
fact a valid entity it successfully was
able to cast it into a player because it
actually was a player and that is
essentially all the dynamic casters if
the cast is valid then it returns the
value that you want to play a pointer
but if it is not valid because it's not
the given type that you've kind of
claimed that it is then it will just
give you not that's what dynamic cast
does in a nutshell now the question that
you should have from this is but how
does it know I haven't written anything
and it's not like C++ or some managed
language like C sharp or Java or
anything like that how how does it know
that player is actually a player like
how does it know that this entity that I
have is actually a player and not an
enemy what the way that it does that is
it actually stores runtime type
information especially what it's called
our TTI
runtime type information it stores
runtime type information about all of
our types this does add an overhead but
it lets you do things like dynamic
casting so there's two things to
consider here first of all our TTI adds
overhead because suddenly types type
types need to store more information
about themselves than were otherwise
present and big or to dynamic cast is
also also takes time because we need to
actually check to see does the type
information match is this entity
actually an enemy or is it a player what
type is that we have to do that
validation at runtime
anytime we dynamic cost so because of
that it does add that overhead now what
we can actually do in our code here is
turn runtime type information off if we
don't need it
so if we go to our properties and it's
different favorite compiler but over
here inside safe c++ and language and
visual studio you can see we have this
enable runtime type information if we
were to switch that off and then we
attempted to compile our code you would
see that it actually would give us a
warning which says dynamic class used on
polymorphic type entity with this just
means that we've switched off runtime
type information so with that with our
TTI off gives us unpredictable behavior
and if we try and run this code and we
hit f10 to get past this invalid dynamic
cast you can see we actually get an
access violation so that actually throws
an error for us all right so it doesn't
doesn't give us null because it can't
because it doesn't have that type
information so make sure that you are
aware of the kind of implications the
dynamic casts actually do because they
do kind of do extra things and they do
require that our TTI is on in most cases
if we were to like for example do a cast
from player to entity which is implicit
anyway it would be fun it wouldn't crash
but if we try and do something like this
you can see it just just it just crashes
doesn't even allow us to it at all and
having our TTI on is pretty typical but
also does add a bit of an overhead so
just keep that in mind one last thing I
want to show you is that because of
dynamic because we have dynamic casts
you know we can do that validation that
I mentioned we can do something like if
p0 now this is very similar to manage
languages like C sharp or Java where we
can basically try and check what is what
something actually is so this actually
enemy you know in like c-sharp we could
do if if is if actually enemy is a
player then we can do it all over in
Java we have instance of so by using
this kind of dynamic cast thing we can
basically achieve the same thing we can
say if dynamic cosplayer actually enemy
right if actually enemy is a player
instance then we can do the following
code and if I just complete this you'll
see that that's perfectly valid right
but obviously we want to kind of cast it
again and use it probably in that okay
so therefore we'd probably do something
like this this kind of code is pretty
typical you see it all the time
but just be aware that dynamic casting
does incur a cost so if you're all about
optimization if you try and write with
really fast code you'll probably want to
avoid that and I hope you guys enjoyed
that video you can hit the like button
you can also help support everything
that I do on patreon for - the Cherno
and I'll see you next time goodbye
[Music]